Register of the Vrangel' collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Vrangel' collection
1916-1929
27001
Hoover Institution Archives
164 manuscript boxes, 14 oversize boxes, 59 maps (90.4 linear feet)
Reports, orders, correspondence, memoranda, dispatches, financial records, minutes, printed matter, maps, and photographs relating to Russian military operations in France during World War I; White Russian diplomatic activities and military operations, especially in southern Russia, during the Russian Revolution and Civil War, including military purchasing and intelligence operations; administration of territory under White Russian control during the Civil War; the evacuation of White Russian military personnel and civilians from the Crimea in 1920; and the resettlement of Russian refugees in Turkey and various European countries. Includes records of the Russian Expeditionary Corps in France, the Volunteer Army, the Armed Forces of Southern Russia, the Northwestern Army, the Foreign Supply Directorate, military representatives in foreign countries and attached to the Allied Supreme Command, and the Russian Army in exile, and some personal papers of Baron Petr Vrangel', commander-in-chief successively of the Armed Forces of Southern Russia and Russian Army. The majority of the collection is also available on microfilm (220 reels). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Vrangel', Petr Nikolaevich, Baron, 1878-1928.
Russia. Armii͡a. Ėkspedit͡sīonnyĭ korpus vo Frant͡sīi.
Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920)
Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920). Dobrovol'cheskaia armiia.
Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920). Severo-Zapadnaia armiia.
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUge Rossii.
Russkai͡a armii͡a.
Access
Microfilm use only (except for box 176 and maps and photographs that have not been microfilmed, as noted in container list). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (220 reels), except for box 176 and maps and photographs noted in container list. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Baron Petr Vrangel'
1878 August 15 Born, Novo-Aleksandrovsk (Zaraisk), Russia into family of Baltic nobility. Spent childhood and youth in Rostov-na-Donu. Received engineering degree from Gornyi Institut Imperatritsy Ekateriny II, St. Petersburg
1901-1902 Completed requirements of Nikolaevskoe Kavaleriiskoe Uchilishche (I-yi razriad)) and Nikolaevskaia Akademiia General'nago SHtaba (I-yi razriad). Commissioned cornet in Gvardeiskaia Kavaleriia
1904-1905 Took part in Russo-Japanese War with 2-oi Argunskii Kazachii Polk and later Otdl'nyi Divizion Razvedchikov. Received decorations and promotion for bravery
1906 Began service in Leib-Gvardii Konnyi Polk
1910 Completed courses of Akademiia General'nago SHtaba
1914-1917 Took part in World War I. Began as Captain of Cavalry, received St. George's Cross for bravery in the field; promoted to rank of colonel
1915 Appointed commander of Nerchinskii Polk, Zabaikal'skoe Kazachee Voisko
1916 Promoted to Maj.-Gen. and given command of Ussuriiskaia Konnaia Diviziia
1917 Resigned from army
1918-1919 Joined Volunteer Army in Ekaterinodar. Appointed commander of 1-ia Konnaia Diviziia and promoted to Lieut.-Gen. by Lieut.-Gen. A. Denikin. Later given command of Volunteer Army and Army of the Caucasus
1920 February Resigned from army
1920 March Appointed Commander-in-Chief of Vooruzhennyia Sily IUga Rossii (V.S.IU.R.) and Military Governor of South Russia. Attempted to reorganize army and carry out land and local government reform
1920 November After fall of White Movement, organized evacuation of V.S.IU.R. and civilian refugees first to Constantinople and later to Balkans. Established headquarters of Russian army-in-exile in Sremski Karlovci, Yugoslavia
1928 April 25 Died, Brussels, Belgium
Scope and Content
The Vrangel' collection is composed of a group of official archives belonging to Russian government agencies and military departments active during World War I, the Russian Civil War, and the first period of Russian emigration. The collection was originally organized by Lieutenant-General N. Golovin in 1927. Each archive within the collection was retained as an independent entity, while at the same time the collection as a whole was divided into 353 files. The present register maintains this arrangement while attempting to greatly expand the description of material found in individual files.
World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Campaigns.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Ukraine--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Refugees.; Russians--Turkey.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; International relief.; Russia. Armii͡a--Officers.
- RUSSKII EKSPEDITSIONNYI KORPUS VO FRANTSII, 1916-1920 (Boxes 1-27)
  Scope and Contents note
  Day-orders, official correspondence, and other documentary material related to the Russian Expeditionary Force in France and on the Saloniki Front. Includes correspondence with Allied Command, especially Ministère de la Guerre, France. Also includes archive of Zavedyvaiushchii Voenno-Sudnoi CHast'iu pri Russkikh Voiskakh vo Frantsii and Voennyi Prokuror Russkikh Voisk vo Frantsii. Files 1-5, 223-235, 252-312.
  - Day-orders to Russian troops in France and on the Saloniki Front
    - Russkiia voiska vo Frantsii, Paris, mimeograph copies
      - No. 1-163 (File 290), 1917
        - May 21-July 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
          Access
          Available on microfilm reel 1
        - August 1-31 (Folder 2)
        - September 1-29 (Folder 3)
        - October 1-31 (Folder 4)
        - November 1-21 (Folder 5)
        - December 6-21 (Folder 6)
      - No. 169-186, January 5-10, 1918 (Folder 7)
    - I-ia Osobaia pekhotnaia diviziia. Day-orders
      - I-yi Marshevoi batalion (Osobo-marshevoi batalion)
        - 1916
          - Irkutsk
            - No. 1-30 (File 300), January 2-31 (Folder 8)
            - No. 31-59 (File 301), February 1-29 (Folder 9)
          - Parakhod "Tambov"
            - No. 60-90 (File 305), March 1-31 (Folder 10)
            - No. 91-121 (File 306), April 1-30 (Folder 11)
          - Mallie
            - No. 122-152 (File 303), May 1-31 (Folder 12)
            - No. 153-182 (File 304), June 1-30 (Folder 13)
            - No. 183-213 (File 307), July 1-31 (Box 2, Folder 1)
              Available on microfilm reel 2
            - No. 214-244A (File 308), August 1-31 (Folder 2)
            - No. 245-274 (File 309), September 1-30 (Folder 3)
            - No. 275-305 (File 310), October 1-31 (Folder 4)
            - No. 306-335 (File 311), November 1-30 (Folder 5)
            - No. 336-366 (File 312), December 1-31 (Folder 6)
        - Maillie, 1917
          - No. 1-31 (File No. 291), January 1-31 (Folder 7)
          - No. 32-59 (File 292), February 1-28 (Folder 8)
          - No. 60-90 (File 293), March 1-31 (Box 3, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 3
          - No. 91-120 (File 294), April 1-30 (Folder 2)
          - No. 121-151 (File 295), May 1-30 (Folder 3)
          - No. 152-212 (File 296), June 1-July 31 (Folder 4)
          - No. 213-271 (File 297), August 1-September 28 (Folder 5)
          - No. 274-365 (File 298), October 1-December 31 (Folder 6)
            Available on microfilm reel 4
        - No. 1-17 (File 299), January 1, 1918-September 13, 1919 (Folder 7)
      - II-oi Marshevoi batalion (File 227)
        - No. 300-847, 1917
          - October 5-27 (Box 4, Folder 1)
          - November 1-30 (Folder 2)
        - No. 1-59, 1918
          - December 1, 1917-February 13 (Folder 3)
          - March 3-July 17 (Folder 4)
    - II-ia Osobaia pekhotnaia diviziia
      - By-orders
        - No. 1-25 (File 278), March 1-November 29, 1916 (Folder 5)
        - No. 216-238, to troops of Moscow garrison (File 279), August 1916 (Folder 6)
      - Day-orders to the staff
        - No. 1-204 (File 280), 1917
          - May 25-July 31 (Folder 7)
          - August 1-31 (Folder 8)
          - September 1-30 (Folder 9)
          - October 1-31 (Folder 10)
          - November 2-30 (Folder 11)
            Available on microfilm reel 5
          - December 1-30 (Folder 12)
        - No. 1-28 (File 280), 1918
          - January 2-31 (Folder 13)
          - February 1-March 10 (Folder 14)
      - Day-orders
        - General
          - No. 3-227 (File 278), 1917
            - May 25-June 30 (Folder 15)
            - July 2-30 (Folder 16)
            - August 2-31 (Folder 17)
            - September 1-30 (Folder 18)
            - October 1-31 (Folder 19)
            - November 1-29 (Folder 20)
            - December 4-27 (Folder 21)
          - No. 1-59 (File 279), January-March 1918 (Box 5, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 6
        - Luzhskii voennyi komitet (File 279), March 14-June 24, 1917 (Folder 2)
        - Komanda vyzdoravlivaiushchikh, Verrie (File 234-235)
          - No. 1-194, 1917-1918
            - July 1-31 (Box 6, Folder 1)
            - August 1-31 (Folder 2)
            - September, 1-31 (Folder 3)
            - October 1-31 (Folder 4)
            - November 1-December 1 (Folder 5)
            - December 2-31 (Folder 6)
            - January 1-February 18, 1918 (Folder 7)
            - No. 1-95 (File 235), 1917
            - September 29-October 30 (Folder 8)
              Available on microfilm reel 6A
            - November 1-30 (Folder 9)
            - December 1-31 (Folder 10)
          - No. 1-45, 1918, January 1-February 14 (Folder 11)
        - Divizionnyi oboz (File 287)
          - No. 1-208, 1917
            - May 1-June 30 (Box 7, Folder 1)
              Available on microfilm reel 7
            - July 1-30 (Folder 2)
            - August 4-31 (Folder 3)
            - September 1-30 (Folder 4)
            - October 1-30 (Folder 5)
            - November 1-30 (Folder 6)
            - December 1-31 (Folder 7)
          - No. 1-30, January 1-February 30, 1918 (Folder 8)
    - I-ia Osobaia pekhotnaia brigada. Day-orders
      - General
        - No. 1-261 (File 276), 1916
          - January 3-April 30 (Folder 9)
          - May 1-31 (Folder 10)
          - June 1-July 31 (Folder 11)
          - August 1-September 30 (Folder 12)
          - October 1-31 (Folder 13)
          - November 2-December 15 (Folder 14)
        - Administrative and Intendancy Services
          - (File 302), January-May 1916 (Folder 15)
    - II-ia Osobaia pekhotnaia brigada (Salonikskii front)
      - Day-orders to the staff (File 280)
        - No. 1-68, 1916
          - June 1-September 30 (Box 8, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 8
          - October 1-December 31 (Folder 2)
        - No. 1-57, January 1-May 30, 1917 (Folder 3)
      - Day-orders
        - General (File 277)
          - No. 1-186, and No. 1-186, 1916, 1917
            - May 9-July 30 (Folder 4)
            - August 1-29 (Folder 5)
            - September 1-October 31 (Folder 6)
            - November 1-December 27 (Folder 7)
          - No. 1-117, 1917
            - January 1-February 28 (Folder 8)
            - March 1-30 April (Folder 9)
            - May 1-22 (Folder 10)
              Available on microfilm reel 9
        - Marshevoi batalion
          - No. 30-204 (File 223), 1916
            - June 9-30 (Folder 11)
            - July 1-30 (Folder 12)
            - September 1-30 (Folder 13)
            - October 1-31 (Folder 14)
            - November 1-30 (Folder 15)
            - November 16-30 (Folder 16)
          - No. 205-235 (File 224), 1916
            - December
              - 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 1)
                Available on microfilm reel 10
              - 16-31 (Folder 2)
          - No. 1-59, 1917
            - January 1-31 (Folder 3)
            - February
              - 1-15 (Folder 4)
              - 16-28 (Folder 5)
          - No. 60-149 (File 225), 1917
            - March 1-30 (Folder 6)
            - Apr
              - 1-15 (Folder 7)
              - 16-30 (Folder 8)
            - May
              - 2-15 (Folder 9)
                Available on microfilm reel 11
              - 16-31 (Folder 10)
          - No. 152-243 (File 226), 1917
            - June
              - 1-14 (Folder 11)
              - 16-30 (Folder 12)
            - July
              - 1-14 (Box 10, Folder 1)
              - 16-29 (Folder 2)
            - August
              - 1-15 (Folder 3)
              - 16-30 (Folder 4)
          - No. 244-364 (File 228), 1917
            - September
              - 1-15 (Folder 5)
              - 16-30 (Folder 6)
            - October 1-30 (Folder 7)
            - November 1-30 (Folder 8)
              Available on microfilm reel 12
            - December 1-30 (Folder 9)
          - No. 1-43, January 1-February 28, 1918 (Folder 10)
    - III-ia Osobaia pekhotnaia brigada. Day-orders
      - General
        - No. 1-130 (File 281), 1917
          - January 1-29 (Folder 11)
          - February 2-27 (Folder 12)
          - March 5-28 (Folder 13)
          - April 11-28 (Folder 14)
          - May 1-24 (Folder 15)
      - Marshevoi batalion osobago naznacheniia
        - No. 1-148 (File 229), 1916
          - June 14-July 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 13
          - July 3-24 (Folder 2)
          - August 20-September 24 (Folder 3)
          - September 26-October 5 (Folder 4)
        - No. 149-254 (File 230), 1916
          - October 8-31 (Folder 5)
          - November 1-30 (Folder 6)
          - December
            - 1-14 (Folder 7)
              Available on microfilm reel 14
            - 16-31 (Folder 8)
    - IV-ia Osobaia pekhotnaia brigada
      - Day-orders to the staff (File 282)
        - No. 1-28, June 6-December 31, 1916 (Folder 9)
        - No. 1-89, 1917
          - January 1-March 29 (Folder 10)
          - April 1-June 20 (Folder 11)
      - Day-orders
        - General
          - No. 1-98 (File 282), 1916
            - June 1-July 31 (Box 12, Folder 1)
            - August 1-October 31 (Folder 2)
            - November 1-December 31 (Folder 3)
          - No. 1-128, 1917
            - January 1-February 28 (Folder 4)
              Available on microfilm reel 15
            - March 3-April 30 (Folder 5)
            - May 2-June 16 (Folder 6)
        - Marshevoi batalion
          - No. 4-187 (File 231), 1917
            - January
              - 4-20 (Folder 7)
              - 22-31 (Folder 8)
            - February
              - 1-17 (Folder 9)
              - 18-28 (Folder 10)
            - March
              - 1-19 (Folder 11)
              - 20-31 (Folder 12)
            - Apr.
              - 1-15 (Folder 13)
              - 16-30 (Folder 14)
            - May
              - 2-20 (Folder 15)
                Available on microfilm reel 16
              - 21-31 (Folder 16)
            - June 2-30 (Folder 17)
          - No. 188-388 (File 232), 1917
            - July 1-31 (Box 13, Folder 1)
            - August
              - 1-15 (Folder 2)
              - 16-31 (Folder 3)
            - September 1-30 (Folder 4)
            - October 1-30 (Folder 5)
            - November 1-30 (Folder 6)
            - December 1-30 (Folder 7)
    - I-ia Osobaia artilleriiskaia brigada. By-orders, No. 1-103 (File 284), May 23-28, 1917 (Folder 8)
      Available on microfilm reel 17
      - II-oi divizion. By-orders, No. 59-99 (File 284), May 13-June 14, 1917 (Folder 9)
    - II-ia Osobaia artilleriiskaia brigada
      - General
        - Day-orders, No. 1-240 (File 285)
          - 1917
          - February 6-March 31 (Folder 10)
          - April 1-30 (Folder 11)
          - May 1-31 (Folder 12)
          - June 1-July 31 (Folder 13)
          - August 1-November 29 (Folder 14)
          - December 1-31 (Folder 15)
          - 1918, January 4-February 8 (Folder 16)
        - By-orders, No. 1-, 1917
          - February 6-March 24 (Folder 17)
          - April 3-30 (Folder 18)
          - May 2-December 30 (Folder 19)
      - I-yi divizion
        - Day-orders, No. 47-284 and No. 1-17 (File 283)
          - 1917
            - April 1-June 31 (Box 14, Folder 1)
            - July 1-August 31 (Folder 2)
            - September 2-30 (Folder 3)
            - October 2-31 (Folder 4)
            - November 1-30 (Folder 5)
            - December 1-31 (Folder 6)
              Available on microfilm reel 18
          - 1918, January 1-17 (Folder 7)
        - By-orders, April 1-May 18, 1917 (Folder 8)
      - II-oi divizion
        - Day-orders, No. 143-209 (File 284), 1917
          - July 6-August 31 (Folder 9)
          - September 2-October 18 (Folder 10)
        - By-orders (File 284), 1917
          - No. 2-59, February 10-May 13 (Folder 11)
          - No. 103-293
            - November 7-December 20 (Folder 12)
            - June 18-November 29 (Folder 13)
      - No. 120-271 (File 252), 1917
        - May
          - 2-15 (Folder 14)
          - 16-31 (Folder 15)
        - June 1-30 (Folder 16)
        - July 1-31 (Folder 17)
        - August 1-31 (Folder 18)
    - II-oi Osobyi pekhotnyi polk. Day-orders
      - No. 319-404 (File 253), October-December 1916
        - October 14-31 (Box 15, Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 19
        - November 1-30 (Folder 2)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 3)
      - No. 2-138 (File 254), January-March 1917
        - January
          - 1-15 (Folder 4)
          - 16-31 (Folder 5)
        - February
          - 1-15 (Folder 6)
          - 17-28 (Folder 7)
        - March
          - 1-15 (Folder 8)
          - 16-31 (Folder 9)
      - No. 140-232 (File 255), April-June 1917
        - April
          - 1-19 (Folder 10)
            Available on microfilm reel 20
          - 19-30 (Folder 11)
        - May 1-15 (Folder 12)
        - 16-June 1 (Folder 13)
      - No. 233-334 (File 256), June-August 1917
        - June
          - 1-9 (Folder 14)
          - 10-24 (Folder 15)
        - July
          - 1-18 (Box 16, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 21
          - 19-31 (Folder 2)
        - August
          - 1-15 (Folder 3)
          - 16-30 (Folder 4)
      - No. 335-474 (File 257), September-November 1917
        - September
          - 1-15 (Folder 5)
          - 15-30 (Folder 6)
        - November 1-15 (Folder 7)
          - 16-December 1 (Folder 8)
    - No. 475-521 (File 258), December 1-31, 1917 (Folder 9-10)
      - No. 1-65, 1918
        - January 6-31 (Folder 11)
        - February 3-26 (Folder 12)
        - March 1-31 (Folder 13)
        - April 4-23 (Folder 14)
        - May 2-25 (Folder 15)
        - June 1-August 25 (Folder 16)
        - September 10-December 16 (Folder 17)
      - No. 1-12, January 1-August 31, 1919 (Folder 18)
    - III-ii Osobyi pekhotnyi polk. Day-orders
      - No. 1-249 (File 259), 1916
        - May 10-31 (Box 17, Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 22
        - June 1-30 (Folder 2)
        - July 1-31 (Folder 3)
        - August 1-30 (Folder 4)
        - September 1-30 (Folder 5)
        - October 2-30 (Folder 6)
        - November 1-30 (Folder 7)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 8)
      - No. 1-238 (File 260), 1917
        - January 1-31 (Folder 9)
        - February 1-28 (Folder 10)
          Available on microfilm reel 23
        - March 1-31 (Folder 11)
        - April
          - 1-22 (Folder 12)
          - 23-30 (Folder 13)
        - May 1-31 (Folder 14)
        - June 1-30 (Folder 15)
        - July
          - 1-14 (Folder 16)
            Available on microfilm reel 24
          - 1-31 (Folder 17)
      - No. 239-414 (File 261), 1917
        - August
          - 1-15 (Box 18, Folder 1)
          - 16-31 (Folder 2)
        - September 1-30 (Folder 3)
        - October 1-31 (Folder 4)
        - November 1-30 (Folder 5)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 6)
        - December 5-31 (Folder 7)
      - No. 1-36, January 1-February 21, 1918 (Folder 8)
    - IV-yi Osobyi pekhotnyi polk. Day-orders
      - No. 1-56 (File 262), 1916
        - May 10-31 (Folder 9)
          Available on microfilm reel 25
        - June 1-30 (Folder 10)
        - July 1-31 (Folder 11)
        - August 1-31 (Folder 12)
        - September 1-30 (Folder 13)
      - No. 157-264 (File 263), 1916
        - October 1-31 (Folder 14)
        - November 1-30 (Folder 15)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 16)
      - No. 1-46, 1917
        - 1, January 1-February (Folder 17)
          Available on microfilm reel 26
        - February 3-28 (Folder 18)
      - No. 47-243 (File 264), 1917
        - March 1-31 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        - April 1-17 (Folder 2)
        - April 18-May 31 (Folder 3)
        - June 1-30 (Folder 4)
        - July 1-28 (Folder 5)
        - August 1-31 (Folder 6)
        - September 1-13 (Folder 7)
          Available on microfilm reel 27
      - No. 244-365 (File 265), 1917
        - September 14-30 (Folder 8)
        - October 1-31 (Folder 9)
        - November 1-31 (Folder 10)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 11)
      - No. 1-48, 1918
        - January 1-31 (Folder 12)
        - February 1-March 12 (Folder 13)
    - VII-oi Osobyi pekhotnyi polk. Day-orders
      - No. 1-234 (File 266), 1916
        - June 1-30 (Box 20, Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 28
        - July 1-31 (Folder 2)
        - August 1-31 (Folder 3)
        - September 1-30 (Folder 4)
        - October 1-31 (Folder 5)
        - November 1-30 (Folder 6)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 7)
      - No. 1-292 (File 267), 1917
        - January 2-31 (Folder 8)
        - February 1-28 (Folder 9)
        - March 1-31 (Folder 10)
          Available on microfilm reel 29
        - April 1-30 (Folder 11)
        - May 1-31 (Folder 12)
        - June 1-30 (Folder 13)
        - July 1-31 (Folder 14)
        - August 1-30 (Folder 15)
      - No. 293-435 (File 268), 1917
        - September 1-30 (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - October
          - 1-15 (Folder 2)
          - 16-31 (Folder 3)
        - November
          - 1-15 (Folder 4)
            Available on microfilm reel 30
          - 16-30 (Folder 5)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 6)
      - No. 1-88 (File 269), 1916
        - June 1-30 (Folder 7)
        - July
          - 1-20 (Folder 8)
          - 21-31 (Folder 9)
        - August
          - 1-20 (Folder 10)
          - 21-24 (Folder 11)
      - No. 89-199 (File 270), September-December 1916
        - September 8-29 (Box 22, Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 31
        - October
          - 1-19 (Folder 2)
          - 20-31 (Folder 3)
        - November 1-30 (Folder 4)
        - December 1-31 (Folder 5)
      - No. 1-231 (File 271), January-June 1917
        - January 1-31 (Folder 6)
        - February 1-28 (Folder 7)
        - March 1-31 (Folder 8)
        - April 1-30 (Folder 9)
        - May 1-31 (Folder 10)